Phillip: Good communication in the workplace
should be effective, but there are often barriers
that can affect this, so let’s have a look at
what they are and how we can overcome them.
Maddy: Cultural differences-These often
occur when the kind of language being used,
such as the use of vocabulary or style, is
unsuitable or unfamiliar to the receiver.
This might be because the two people
involved are used to different workplace
cultures, so may find one another’s style
of communicating unfamiliar and challenging.
Phillip: The important thing about overcoming
language barriers is to establish a common ground
that both sender and receiver are familiar with.
This will make communication
smoother and more reliable.
It's also important to bear in mind who
the audience is and what you can do to make
the language more appropriate for them?
Maddy: Inattention and a lack of engagement-
This may mean that neither the sender, the
receiver, or both really care about communicating,
so not enough attention is being paid.
Communication doesn’t work if the people involved
don’t care about what’s being communicated.
If they don’t care, they won’t make
the effort to communicate properly, or
care about the message they receive.
Phillip: It's important that the sender
invests time and energy into making the
communication relevant to the receiver
making it clear why it is important for them.
In turn receivers should try to avoid distractions
when they receive a message, so they can focus on
it fully and ask follow-up questions if needed.
Maddy: Information overload- This can involve
too much information being communicated,
and this could either be because the
wrong channel is being used, or the
information hasn't been coded correctly.
If we try to communicate too much information
in one go, it won’t work because the
person receiving may feel overwhelmed,
with all the facts being thrown at them.
Some methods are more flexible
with how much information they can
effectively transmit, than others.
Phillip: Senders need to be mindful of how
much information they need to communicate
and how much they are communicating.
It's easy to go into too much detail
about irrelevant points sometimes.
So remember in general, the shorter the
message, the easier it is to understand
[though that doesn't mean you should omit
important details if they're necessary].
Maddy: Distractions and noise- These can be
literal, such as if you're trying to have a
sensitive conversation in a noisy business
area, or it can be more general, like if an
email is cluttered with unnecessary pictures.
Distractions and noise pull the ‘receiver’
away from the point of the communication,
meaning they might walk away not realising or
understanding what the point was meant to be.
Phillip: Keep communications
clear and to the point.
Don't throw in visuals or graphics or
fancy phrases just for the sake of them.
Everything in the message should
have a reason to be there.
And remember to make sure that conversations
happen somewhere quiet and private,
especially if they're on a sensitive subject.
Maddy: Emotions- In nonverbal and oral
communication, it’s easy to let our emotions
get the better of us and undermine our message.
Although there’s often a place for some
emotional expression in communication, it can
also sometimes inhibit effective communication.
That’s because the way we’re feeling, can
often cloud our rational mind, meaning we’re
not receptive to what’s actually being said.
We might feel that something unfair
has been said, meaning we don’t
want to listen to valid criticism.
Or we might feel so frustrated about
a situation that our communications
sound angry and aggressive.
Phillip: It’s important to remember human beings
aren't robots and there's nothing wrong with
your emotions coming through in communication!
But you need to consider how you're
expressing your feelings, and if it's
appropriate to do so at that time.
Being too emotive or trying to provoke
an emotional response in the receiver,
might not always be appropriate.
Maddy: Lack of clarity- This could be
due to poor encoding or an inappropriate
channel, the information in the message
just isn't clear to the receiver or isn’t
interpreted in the way you meant it to be.
If this happens then this
is a failed communication.
Phillip: If a communication is too
vague or too long, the receiver may
feel like they're time is being wasted.
They'll lose focus and miss important information.
Your communications should
be direct and to the point.
Avoid using complicated imagery or metaphors and
be clear about the purpose of the communication.
Maddy: Wrong style and tone -The message
could be using the right channel,
but is too formal and impersonal, or
the opposite too informal and casual.
This means that the receiver won’t be as
receptive to the message because it won’t
feel right to them and will undermine the
communication, making it less effective.
Phillip: Everyone has their own style of
writing and speaking, and that's fine.
In fact, a bit of personality can often make
your communication easier to understand.
But be mindful of your tone and style and
think about what your audience is expecting
from you, and what you need to say.
Think about some of the communications
you have received in the past and how
you might have said things differently.
Maddy: So, there are a range of barriers to
communication in the workplace, but these barriers
can be overcome if you just take some time
to consider how they might be received and if
you could communicate in a more effective way.